All right. Now we're doing the second part of the project walkthrough. I'm Erin.
ではプロジェクトの 2番目へ進みますエリンです
I'm Steven.
スティーブンです
And so far, we've looked at how to get waypoints.
これまで どのようにウェイポイントへ到達するかを見てきました
Now we need this car to actually follow waypoints.
ここでは この車が実際にウェイポイントを追跡する必要があります
Yeah. Well, let's have a look.
そのとおりでは実際に見てみましょう
Yeah, let's see how we get started.
それではどのように始めるか見てみましょう
For this section, we're going to be looking at the DbW Node.
このセクションでは DbW ノードを見ていきます
Okay, that's the next concept here right after the Waypoint Updater.
OK ここでの次のコンセプトは Waypoint Updater のすぐ後ですね
So, what are we working with here?
では ここでは何を行いますか?
So right away, I'm seeing some throttle commands,
ここにすぐに throttle コマンド
break commands, steering commands.
break コマンド steering コマンドがあります
Yeah. If your DbW Node is going to be subscribing to the twist command topic,
そうですね皆さんの DbW ノードが twist コマンドトピックをサブスクライブしている場合
so once final Waypoints are published,
最終 Waypoints がパブリッシュされると
they go to the waypoint follower which is some Autoware software that takes
Autoware ソフトウェアの一種であるウェイポイントフォロワーへ進み
the final waypoints and
最終ウェイポイントと
their velocities and then publishes appropriate twist commands for the car.
その速度を取って車のための適切な twist コマンドをパブリッシュします
So, twists commands, if you haven't seen them before,
twists コマンドをご覧になったことない方へ説明すると
basically just linear and angular accelerations for the car.
基本的には車の線形加速度および角加速度となります
Looks like it'll have lot of different kinds of controllers here.
ここで さまざまな種類のコントローラーをお見せします
Yeah, and you're going to need some controllers to control the car probably.
おそらく 車を制御するためにいくつかのコントローラーが必要となるでしょう
Yeah, a lot of these are just kind of given to you, right?
たくさんの種類が提供されていますね?
Yeah.
そのとおり
So, like PID that's given low pass filter.
たとえば PID はローパスフィルターで提供されます
This node will take in twist command topic messages,
このノードは twist コマンドトピックメッセージを取得します
and then what you want to do is publish throttle, steering and break.
ここで実行したいのは スロットル ステアリング ブレーキをパブリッシュすることです
Okay, let's go ahead and check out the code.
では コードを確認してみましょう
So, I'm interested in this dbw_node.py which I found in twist controller.
twist コントローラーのところで見つけた dbw_node.py に興味があります
So, this is what it looks like when I first open it up.
これが最初にファイルを開いたときの様子です
So, this one has some of the basic code already set up for you,
ここには既に設定済みの複数の基本コードが実装されていて
here a bunch of car parameters,
ここにたくさんのカーパラメーターがあり
you may need to use all of these car parameters.
これらすべてのカーパラメーターを使用することになるでしょう
Yeah. Do I really need the fuel capacity?
そうですね本当にfuel capacity (燃料容量) は必要ですか?
If you want to be really precise,
精度を求めるなら
you can use the fuel capacity,
燃料容量が使用できます
because you will need the vehicle weight when you're stopping the car.
車の停止の時に車両重量が必要となりますからね
Had a hard time figuring out what the fuel capacity should be in a simulator.
シミュレーターに燃料容量を取り込むと 計算が大変になりますね
Yeah. So, it's not going to work in the simulator although
まったくまあ シミュレーターではこれは使用しません
That was infinite.
それは無限ですから
Infinite fuel. So, it can go forever.
無限の燃料 では 走り続けられますね
But that's like to control how heavy the car is,
しかし これは車の重量を制御するような方法ですから
so you have fuel capacity.
燃料容量が実装されています
If you know it's like 75 percent for its gas,
もしガソリンの 75 パーセントであるとわかっている場合
then you can actually factor in the mass of that.
その値をファクターとして使用できます
You can get really precise,
高い精度を求めることもできますが
but for our purposes, you won't need that.
ここでの目的では その必要はありません
But you will need the wheel radius and the vehicle mass.
ただし ホイール半径と車両重量が必要です
Okay, so I can do some basic physics here.
OK では基本的な物理が使えますね
Yeah, because break commands should be in units of torque.
はい、ブレーキコマンドはトルクの単位を扱いますからね
Oh, that's right. Newton meters.
はい そのとおりですニュートンメートルですね
And so, to figure out how much torque you should be applying the brake,
そして ブレーキにどれくらいのトルクを適用すべきか求めるために
you're going to be multiplying the vehicle mass,
車両重量 掛ける
times the wheel radius,
ホイール半径 掛ける
times the desired acceleration.
目的の加速度として計算します
Alright. So, we have this loop that's happening again at 50 hertz.
わかりましたまたここで 50 ヘルツ でのループがありますね
Yes.
はい
Is 50 hertz important this time,
ここでは 50 ヘルツが重要ですか
or I can just do 30?
それとも 30 ヘルツにしても大丈夫ですか?
Extremely important this time,
この場合は非常に重要です
previously 30 hertz was not that important,
前回の 30 ヘルツはそれほど重要ではありませんでしたが
50 hertz is essential in this.
この場合 50 が必須となります
The way that the car drive by wire works is that if it does
DBWによって車両を動かす場合
not receive commands at 50 hertz, it complains a little bit.
50ヘルツでコマンドを受信できないと思い通りに動作しません
If it receives them below,
もしそれ以下の値を返された場合
I think 20 hertz or so, then it will just shut off.
20 ヘルツくらいでシャットダウンになると思います
And it does this as a safety feature.
またこれは 安全機能としても働きます
Yeah.
そうですね
So, it thinks that maybe the computer died and so it's
コンピューターの故障とみなし
trying to revert control back to the driver.
ドライバーへ制御を返そうとするでしょう
So, if you're not publishing at 50 hertz,
50 ヘルツをパブリッシュしない場合
chances are your drive by wire might just quit in the middle of testing.
50ヘルツでパブリッシュしないと、DBWによる運転はテスト中に終了することになるでしょう
That's good to know, make a note of that for sure.
知っておいてよかったです 確認のために控えておきましょう
Let's go ahead and check out the resulting code.
では先に進み 結果コードを確認してみましょう
We have some subscribers already just talking about,
既にお話したように サブスクライバーが既にあり
and inside our loop here we have this controller.
ここのループの中にこのコントローラーを実装しています
So, that comes from our twist_controller.py,
これは twist_controller.py から出力しているので
so there's a control class defined there.
定義された制御クラスがそこにあります
So, we've imported a controller from there.
したがって コントローラーをそこからインポートしました
It looks like it's giving us a throttle,
現在の速度を基にした スロットル
a brake and a steering based on its current velocity.
ブレーキ ステアリングが提供されているように見えますね
If DbW is enabled or not, this linear velocity,
DbW が実行可能かどうかにより 線速度や
angular velocity which are all starting out as a none, it looks like.
角速度は none として出発しているようですね
And then, let me guess they are getting filled in by some callback functions.
そして コールバック関数が書き込まれているようですね
Yes, exactly.
はい そのとおり
Okay.
では
All kinds of data coming into this node and we fill those out with the callbacks.
いろいろな種類のデータがこのノードに入り これをコールバックで書き出します
So there's a velocity and I'm publishing throttle,
速度があり スロットル ステアリング
the steering and the break.
ブレーキをパブリッシュします
So, as a sanity check,
きちんとしたチェックでは
I just want to make sure this all is able to send commands to the car.
このすべてがコマンドを車へ送信しているか確認したいですね
I just want the car to drive forward, what could I do?
ただ前進させたい場合 どうすればいいですか?
So, if you just want to test if the car is driving forward,
車が前進することをテストしたいだけの場合
you could set your throttle to one and your steering and break to zero,
スロットルを 1 に ステアリングとブレーキを 0 に設定して
and then just publish throttle.
スロットルをパブリッシュするだけです
So, unlike like break, throttle is in proportion from zero to one.
そしてブレーキのようにではなく スロットルは 0 から 1 とします
Okay, so I can kind of come in this starter function
OK ではスターター関数まで進めて
and then instead of using this actual controller,
このアクチュアルコントローラーを使用する代わりに
I could just hard code the values of throttle,
スロットル ブレーキ ステアリングの値をハードコードして
brake and steering and use these callbacks.
コールバックを使用します
Next we should check out this controller.
次に このコントローラーを確認しましょう
Sure, that's actually where most of the work is going on for this one.
はい 実際にほとんどの作業はこの部分で実行されます
Seems pretty important.
とても重要なようですね
Okay. So when we first open up that controller,
では 最初にコントローラーを開くと
it looks pretty empty.
空っぽのように見えますね
Yeah.
そうですね
It's just returning one zero zero by default.
ただ デフォルトとして 1 0 0 が返ってきているだけですね
Okay. So, I might guess you could call just the controller and that should drive forward.
OKこれだと コントローラーを呼び出して車を前進できそうですね
Okay. Awesome. Let's see what it looks like once you fill it in.
OK素晴らしい書き込むとどうなるか見てみましょう
Sure, there are lots and lots of different ways you can do this,
もちろん ここではものすごくたくさんの方法でいろいろなことができ
lots of ways you can use controllers to control the velocity of the car.
車の速度を制御するコントローラーを使用できる方法もたくさんあります
You are provided with the yaw controller.
yaw コントローラーが提供されています
So, it's helping with this steering?
では これがステアリングをサポートするんですか?
Yeah, so we can get steering commands from the yaw controller,
はい ステアリングコマンドを yaw コントローラーから受け取ったら
and you need to put in the wheelbase steering ratio,
ホイールベースステアリング比を書き込んでください
I believe 0.1 Is the lowest speed of the car in meters per second.
秒速 0.1 メートルが車の最低速度となると思います
Okay.
OK
And then the max lateral acceleration and the max steering angle.
そして最大横加速度と最高ステアリング角度となります
And all of those are parameters that we passed in dbw.py,
さらに これらすべては dbw.py を通過するパラメーターですから
so you just need to forward them to yaw controller.
これを yaw コントローラーへ進めるだけです
And then I have the PID controller as well for the throttle.
さらに スロットルのために PDI コントローラーも実装されていますね
And these parameters for the throttle controller
スロットルコントローラー用のパラメーターは
we're determined completely experimentally,
完全に実験によって得られたもので
there was no- just testing out what worked.
どのように動作するかテストするだけです
It's getting a little bit interesting,
少し面白くなってきました
we have a low pass filter as well.
ローパスフィルターも実装されていますね
So, the low pass filter we've created because
ローパスフィルターを作成したのは
the velocity that's coming in over the messages is kind of noisy,
メッセージを通じてやってくる速度がノイズを含んでいるため
so basically, this LowPassFilter is
基本的に この LowPassFilter が
filtering out all of the high-frequency noise in the velocity.
速度の中の高周波帯のノイズを取り除いてくれるためです
And we also have some vehicle mass, fuel capacity,
また 車両重量 燃料容量や
things that we might need or might not need,
必要かどうかかわからないけど
such as wheel radius,
ホイール半径にように
they'll probably come in handy.
役に立ちそうなものもあります
Acceleration and deceleration limit, you probably want.
加速度や減速度限界は おそらく必要でしょう
That's given to us,
これは与えられていて
the deceleration limit set in a configuration file.
減速限界はコンフィギュレーションファイルに設定します
That comes in, I believe,
これも入ってくると思うのですが
also as one of the Ros params and the other part in dbw_node.py.
ROS パラメーターの一つや dbw_node.py. の他の部分もあります
And is that preset because that is determined by the car itself?
車そのものによって定義されますから これはプリセットですか?
No. I think the acceleration limit and deceleration limit are just comfort parameters.
いいえ 加速度限界と減速度限界はコンフォートパラメーターなだけだと思います
Okay.
OK
So, how fast you want, the maximum amount that you want the car to slow down or speed up.
ですから 速度はどうしたいか 車の減速や加速の最大値をどうしたいか ですね
So we have this control function right here,
ここにコントロールファンクションがありますので
and let's check that out.
確認してみましょう
First of all, what is calling control.
まず初めに コントロールを呼び出すには
Control gets called in dbw.py.
コントロールは dbw.py の中に呼び出されます
So, we create instance of this controller class up above and then we call control,
コントローローラークラスのインスタンスを上記のように作成し
that's 50 hertz basically.
基本的に 50 ヘルツでコントロールを呼び出します
First thing I guess we're checking is dbw_enabled or not,
最初に確認することは dbw_enabled が実行可能かどうかです
why do we care about dbw_enabled?
なぜ dbw_enabled を考えなければならないのでしょう?
So we can turn the drive by wire on and off in the car.
私たちはDBWをONにしたりOFFにすることができます
So as we're sitting, waiting for a traffic light,
信号待ちをしているとき
I might turn the DbW off,
私はDBWをOFFにするかもしれません
or if I'm fixing something else,
また何かを直しているとき
DbW might be off while the code is running.
コードの実行中はDBWはOFFになるかもしれません
If you're using a PID controller and you have an integral term,
PID コントローラーを使用中では 積分の項があり
then if you don't turn the PID controller off,
PID コントローラーをオフにしない場合には
then you'll be accumulating error.
エラーの蓄積が発生します
And that'll be bad because then when we turn the DbW Node back on,
これは良くありません なぜなら DbW ノードに戻った時
you'll have accumulated all this error and the car might do something really erratic.
このすべてのエラーが蓄積され 車が迷走することになりかねません
Oh man, you wouldn't enjoy that.
ああ それは面白くないですね
No.
そのとおりです
So, if it's not enabled, go ahead and return zero zero zero, otherwise.
よって 実行可能でない場合には 先に進んで 0 0 0 を返してください
I'm sure it resets the controller.
これでコントローラーがリセットされますね
Got you.
そのとおりです
Okay. Otherwise, we're going to be taking a look at our current velocity,
OKそうでなければ 現在の速度と
the steering that we're getting from
yaw コントローラーから得るステアリングを調べ
this yaw controller and we're checking out this velocity error.
この速度エラーを確認します
So, where do we want to be versus where we're currently at,
つまり どこへ行きたいかに対して現在どこにいるのか
we have this last velocity value as well,
ここに最終速度もありますね
is this where we start doing some physics?
これが物理的処理を始める場所ですか?
Yeah, down there we start doing physics for the break part.
はい 下にブレーキパートの物理的処理を開始する場所がありますね
For throttle, it looks like we're stepping through our throttle controller.
スロットルでは スロットルコントローラーをステップスルーしているように見えますね
So that's in reference to the PID controller?
これは PID コントローラーと関連していますか?
Yeah. So we have our error, the velocity error,
はい速度エラーと
and the sample time, you know up at the top when we're initializing this class,
サンプル時間があり このクラスで初期化した時にわかっているでしょうけど
we have our current time as the rest by the time and we're able to
残り時間として現在の時間があり
use that to get the sample time for each step of our PID controller.
PID コントローラーの各ステップでサンプルタイムを得るために使用できます
So we're just calling this step right here,
では ここでこのステップを呼び出して
and that's actually what's doing the stepping for our PID controller.
実際にPID コントローラーで実行されているサンプリングとなります
Was there any errors in this that you defined?
定義したエラーがこの中にありますか?
Yeah, actually when I was writing this code,
はい 実際にこのコードを書いているとき
I noticed that the PID controller had an error that
PID コントローラーにエラーがあることに気が付きました
was preventing the integral from getting reset in full term.
それは フルタームの中でのリセットからの積分が妨げられるエラーでした
So I opted at the repo and it should be good now,
ですから repo で選択して今は大丈夫なはずですが
but you'll want to make sure that you have
Capstone Repo からのこの最新バージョンを
the latest version of this from the Capstone Repo.
確認したくなるのではないかと思います
Yeah, it looks like some of these were modified.
そうですね この部分は変更されているように見えますね
You can see I had some debugging terms down there,
いくつかデバグした項がこの下にあるのがわかると思います
the rospy.logwarn just to check out what was going on.
rospy.logwarn は何が実行されているのかを確認しているだけです
So, we got that throttle value and initially we're setting break to zero,
では スロットル値を得て 初期値としてブレーキを 0 に設定したので
and now we're doing a check here.
ここで確認を実行します
This is just a very simple control of the car.
これは とても単純な車の制御です
So first check we're doing is if our linear velocity, that's our target,
最初に実行するチェックは 線形速度 これは私たちの目的ですが
linear velocity is zero,
線形速度が 0
and we are going very slow,
そしてゆっくりと進み
so our current velocity is less than 0.1.
現在の速度が 0.1 以下です
We should probably be trying to stop,
おそらく停止しようとするでしょうから
so what we're gonna do is set the throttle equal to zero and apply a lot of break.
スロットル = 0 として 多量のブレーキを適用します
Or else, throttle's also really small and the velocity error is less than zero.
さもないと スロットルはとても小さく 速度エラーが 0 より小さくなります
Yeah. So in this case,
そうですねこの場合
our velocity is negative,
速度は負の値となり
which means that we're going faster than we want to be, and so,
これは希望する速度よりも速いことを意味しており
faster than our target velocity,
つまり目的速度よりも速いことになります
and our PID is letting up on the throttle but we want to slow down,
また PID はスロットルを緩めますが 私たちは減速したいので
throttle is less than 0.1 and velocity here is negative.
スロットルは 0.1 より小さくなり ここでの速度は負の値となります
And this time we're not just hard coding the break to 400,
この場合 ブレーキを 400 でハードコーディングするのではなく
but we're using this absolute value,
この絶対値を使用して
the deceleration times the vehicle mass and the wheel radius.
減速度に車両重量とホイール半径を掛けます
That gives us the torque that we want,
これで 目的とするトルク値が得られますので
so it's the amount that we want to decelerate,
減速したい値に
times our vehicle mass,
車両重量を掛けて
times the wheel radius.
ホイール半径を掛けます
Vehicle mass is in kilograms,
車両重量はキログラム
wheel radius is in meters.
ホイール半径はメートルです
I'm actually figuring out this deceleration value,
実際に減速値を計算します
it's a max between the velocity error and R-parameter that we defined earlier.
それは速度エラーと前に定義した減速限界パラメータとの最大値です
So this is actually dependent on this velocity error,
したがって これは実際には速度エラーに左右され
so if it is very large,
もし大きい値の場合
this break value could be very large.
このブレーキの値もとても大きくなります
One thing that really tripped me up when I was coding this is
コードを書く際につまずいた部分の一つに
that I was making the break value negative.
ブレーキの値が負の値となることです
I see what's happening there.
なるほど 実際には何が起こっているでしょうか
So I was like, I want to slow down,
たとえば 減速したい場合
acceleration is positive and then break value is negative.
加速度が正の値でブレーキの値は負になります
Of course it wasn't slowing the car down in the simulator at all.
もちろん シミュレーター上で車は全く減速しませんね
That's why you have this absolute value.
だから絶対値を使う必要があるのです
Yeah, exactly, because decel here is going to be
はい そのとおりですね ここで decel は負の値となりますが
a negative number and we want to make it positive.
これを正の値としたいですよね
So, I think that concludes everything for controls.
これでコントロールを完了したと思います
Yeah. At this point you should be publishing on
そうですね ここでウェイポイント上でパブリッシュを行い
your waypoints and they should be coming into your dbw_node.py,
それがdbw_node.pyに入り
and you should have a controller that will control the car.
車を制御するコントローラが得られているはずです
There's one more thing actually we should talk about a little bit.
あともう一つ 実際にお話しておかなければならないことがあります
Something that I noticed when I have the car
この部分で車を動作しているとき
working at this point was that as it was driving along down the road,
道路に沿って進むにつれて
it's still wandered a little bit within lane,
車線の内側から少し離れていることがあります
and that's something that's actually an artifact of the Autoware code that we use.
また時として これが実際に使用している Autoware コードの乱れとなることがあります
So, the Autoware code doesn't recompute your trajectory until
したがって ウェイポイントから一定の距離だけ離れるまで
you've passed a certain distance away from
またはウェイポイントのトラジェクトリーから一定の角度だけ離れるまで
the waypoints or certain angle away from the trajectory of waypoints.
Autoware コードはトラジェクトリーを再計算しません
And I noticed with this very simple controller,
そして注意してほしいのは このとても単純なコントローラーによって
by the time it recomputed the trajectory and gave new twists commands to the car,
トラジェクトリーを再計算して新しい twist コマンドを車に送る時点まで
the car had already sort of wandered away from the waypoints, and so the car,
既に車はウェイポイントから逸れているので
then steers sort of suddenly back to the waypoints.
ウェイポイントへ突然戻ることがあります
And then by the time the waypoint follow in nodes,
ウェイポイントがノードや
some new twists commands we've already wandered over to the other side.
新しい twists コマンドに従うまで 他へ逸れていきます
So you start refreshing cursor.
ですから カーソルをリフレッシュしてください
Yeah, so there are a couple of ways you can fix this,
そうですね これを修正する方法はいくつかありますが
the code should still pass the greater with this setup.
コードはこの設定でさらに大きく超えていくことがあります
Yeah.
そうですよね
It'll just be a little bit wandering.
少しだけ外れているだけかもしれません
But how can we fix it?
しかし これをどのように修正できますか?
So you can go into
そうですね
the waypoint follower CPP code and
ウェイポイントフォロワー CPP コードへ進み
you can look and make sure that it's updating all the time.
常に更新されているかどうか確認することができます
So there's a function in there that checks if you're following the waypoints,
その中にはウェイポイントに従っているかどうかを確認する関数があり
and if you are not following waypoints then it updates.
もしウェイポイントに従っていなければ 更新します
You can modify that code to check basically to follow the waypoints all the time.
コードを変更して 基本的にはいつでもウェイポイントに従うように確認することができます
Other things that you might do would be to
その他にする必要が出てくる場面は
change your yaw controller to dampen the steering a little bit,
yaw コントローラーを変更してステアリングの値をダンプニングしたり
or you have this yaw cntroller,
この yaw コントローラーがある場合
and if you scroll down a little bit, we're calling get_steering.
少しスクロールダウンして get_steering を呼び出します
You could add some dampening terms that take
いくつかのダンプニング項を追加して
your current angular velocity and your target angular velocity,
現在の角速度やターゲット角速度を得たり
and look at the difference between the two.
2 つの差を確認することができます
Okay.
では
And if they're the same,
その 2 つが同じであれば
you won't change the steering,
ステアリングは変更せず
and if they're very different,
もし違えば
you might add some dampening to look in.
ダンプニングをその中に追加します
Now we had that low pass filter,
ここにローパスフィルターがあります
that wasn't doing anything too complicated,
これはそれほど複雑ではありません
it was just averaging a history of values,
値の履歴を平均化するだけで
never got too large because it was dependent on the previous entries as well.
前のエントリーに左右されるため 大きな数には決してなりません
Right, it just takes the signal and takes
そうですね 単に信号を取り
whatever part of the signal is coming in and averages that with the previous part.
入ってくる信号のどの部分でも集めて前の部分と平均化します
And it is waiting at according to that tau frequency parameter.
そして タウ周波数パラメーターに従って待機します
Cool.
素晴らしい
Anything else.
他にありますか
No, I think that's it.
いいえ これで全部です
Awesome.
素晴らしい
Alright. Well, see you next time.
それではまた お会いしましょう